[music]
>> Hello everyone. My name is Zaini Blue
and I work at Astral building
tools for Python developers and today
I'll be talking about how agents use
developer tools, what qualities of tools
are important and how the design of
tools is changing as agentic programming
grows.
So briefly, what are developer tools?
At their core, developer tools are
abstractions that help with parts of the
software development life cycle.
And this includes a lot of things like
issue trackers, programming languages,
compilers, package managers,
etc.
Did I lose my microphone? No, it's good
again.
In this talk I'll be focusing on the
tools that agents interact with when
writing code rather than tools used for
the entire software development life
cycle. That means tools that help with
tasks like writing, inspecting and
running programs.
So
why are tools helpful for agents?
Agents are open-ended systems unlike
most of our tools that do one thing
repeatedly. Agents are generalized and
stochastic. They need feedback to
constrain their solutions. They get some
of this [snorts] feedback through their
own chain of thought and through their
harness which might even include other
agents giving feedback.
However, to build reliable systems
efficiently, we need deterministic and
specialized feedback from tools.
The most important outcome of feedback
is correctness.
If the agent solution is incorrect,
that's clearly going to have negative
consequences. So how do we use tools to
determine correctness? Well, first of
all, you run the code. We usually call
this testing.
Ideally, we do this in a controlled,
scoped and reproducible way which
requires tooling. For example, a package
manager, a test runner, a mocking
library, coverage analyzer.
Another way that we can use feedback to
inform correctness is static analysis.
In this we analyze the code itself
rather than running it. This is
generally faster than running the code
and it doesn't require writing tests. It
can catch untested assumptions and it
can find edge cases that you haven't
accounted for. The most familiar forms
of this are type checkers and linters.
Today we have tools to do this because
humans struggle to reason about it at
scale and agents really struggle with
this too. There's a bunch of research
showing that agents can't do complex
static analysis even if you do
fine-tuning on those kind of tasks.
Aside from correctness, I want to talk
about quality which is another important
trait that we can improve with feedback.
This captures a lot of different
elements like what makes code good.
Is it readable? Is it documented? Is it
well-factored? Are there
vulnerabilities? Does it use deprecated
APIs? Is there dead code? Is it fast? Is
it performant?
These have less short-term implications
than correctness, but they're very
important for the long-term success of
projects.
We also care about traits that aren't
driven by feedback like efficiency.
For example, we care about how long it
takes an agent to finish doing a task.
Similar to humans, while an agent
probably could solve a problem without a
tool. For example,
one of my co-workers complained that the
agent used curl to download a wheel from
PyPI directly and then unzipped it into
their site packages.
That's probably not the most efficient
way to work. Not only does it take time
to perform tasks that could perform
faster by a tool, but it consumes
valuable context. Tools can help agents
be more efficient by specializing in
solving subsets of problems better than
an agent would with an ad-hoc approach.
We also care about safety. The
open-ended nature of agents as well as
the inclusion of untrusted inputs means
that agents can perform undesirable and
surprising actions.
Tools are a key interaction point
between agents and other systems and
while they can greatly empower agents,
they can also be used to provide
boundaries and constraints. For example,
with fine-grained access controls and
sandboxing.
Another important one is that tools
allow agents to learn more about the
state of the world. The canonical
example here is searching for context
across many files using Ripgrep which is
every agent's favorite tool or looking
up the documentation for a function.
So those are all the qualities that I
think are relevant when you're talking
about a single agent interacting with a
tool.
But in agents are inherently scalable in
a way that people are not. You can
quickly quickly scale up to hundreds of
agents and then down to zero again. And
this means that there are higher order
interactions between agents and tools
and we need to consider how tools
interact with many agents.
To help consider the consequences of
this paradigm, imagine if all the
problems faced by teams of 100 plus
engineers become problems commonplace
for teams of 10 engineers.
One change that's really apparent
already is that agents are making it
much easier to produce large quantities
of code. They're dramatically increasing
the amount of code in the world and this
means that tools designed for working at
scale are going to grow in importance.
Today, this isn't necessarily the
bottleneck in most agentic loops because
inference isn't very fast. However,
inference is going to get faster and
tools will become the bottleneck.
We're also seeing scaling problems with
concurrency. People are using many
agents in parallel and delegating work
to agents in the background. Teams of
agents are being used to coordinate on
larger features and people are
increasingly context switching and
supervising agents instead of focusing
on a single task.
An easy example of this changing tool
use is that suddenly everyone is using
Git worktrees which I had not heard of 2
years ago.
As agents scale, reproducibility is also
important. For example, we need to be
able to quickly construct developer
environments for agents and we need to
be able to track changes to those
environments and propagate them back and
merge them together.
A good example of this is using
Terraform to manage infrastructure or
enumerating your dependencies in a
pyproject.toml.
Declarative environments increase the
scope of what agents can effectively
collaborate on.
>> [sighs]
>> So next I want to take all these
concepts and consider how they might
affect our road map and tools. At Astral
we work on a few tools in the Python
ecosystem. Hopefully you've heard of
them. There's Ruff, a linter and
formatter,
Ty, a type checker, and UV, a package
and project manager. In some ways I feel
like our tools are really
well-positioned. They're designed to be
fast regardless of scale. They're built
for declarative workflows and they're
robust in current use.
We expect to continue investing in those
areas, but there are other places that
we need to adjust our focus.
First I'll talk about tool output.
Today our default output targets humans
and agents honestly do pretty well with
that, but there are many ways that we
can optimize our output for agentic use
cases.
Output is the main way that our tools
communicate feedback to agents. So
what's the best way to communicate to an
agent?
Here's what a diagnostic looks like from
Ty, our type checker, today.
I think it's beautiful,
but I'm honestly not sure if it's the
ideal diagnostic for an agent. Do they
need all this context
or is that
I think that
to come to a conclusion here, we would
actually have to
do research assessing agent performance
on different output formats because it's
not immediately clear.
Some decisions are easier. For example,
we've been long considering a review
mode for Ruff. This is a design that I
wrote in 2023 when I first joined
Astral. I was working on a Ruff CLI RFC
for the future work. And a review mode
here would allow you to interactively
view each violation in your code, accept
a fix, add a suppression, etc. in a TUI.
But now interactive feedback feels like
it would serve too few of our users and
I just don't think we'll end up working
on this.
Next I want to talk about reducing
context consumption and output for more
efficient tool use. Machine-readable
output is an obvious first step here
allowing the agent to compose with tools
like JQ to access the subset of data
that they need so they're not eating
into the context with each tool call.
However, right now using JSON output can
actually increase verbosity. So this is
a comparison between the
default output of UV and the JSON output
for UV sync when you're just validating
that an environment is up to date. If we
were installing packages, it wouldn't
fit on the slide at all for the JSON
output so I couldn't use an example with
that. Clearly this isn't a context
reduction on its own. The agent needs to
actually subset the data,
but how does the agent know what's
available so it can pick out what it
needs? If we were a tool that existed 10
years ago, it would be in the training
set, but we're a new tool. If we're
adding new JSON outputs in machine
readable formats, how do we teach agents
about those?
Uh there are a few different approaches
here. Uh here's one idea. Uh we could
just build context reduction to the tool
itself. Um UV is best suited to decide
which fields are important, and so
instead of showing that whole JSON blob,
we can show the things that we think are
important, and then allow the agent to
opt in to uh fetching data from
additional fields.
A challenge with that then is that the
agent needs to run the commands multiple
times to get the output they need.
Uh the classic example here is the agent
repeatedly tailing the output to get
more logs while debugging, increasing
the number each time. And while UV is
really fast, like not all commands are
free to run repeatedly like that, and uh
UV like even has to do quite a bit of
work on each of those operations, and
that won't scale once you have hundreds
of agents.
A way to solve this is to persist the
output and give the agent to a pointer
uh give the agent a pointer to a file
instead.
Uh then the agent is receiving reduced
context by default, and it can always
investigate further as needed. Um this
is applicable beyond machine readable
output. For example, when something goes
wrong, you need to run the command again
with a verbose flag to get logs. Um we
could just store those verbose logs in a
file uh
always, and then
uh allow fetching them from that file
afterwards. Uh this exists in some tools
today already. Uh we've actually seen
that and liked it and explored adding it
to UV, uh but it hasn't felt critical
until now.
I want to move on to another roadmap
item other than outputs. Uh so I want to
talk about language servers.
Uh language servers, or LSPs, uh power a
lot of human interaction with
programming languages in editors.
Um and we're pretty actively working on
a language server in TY, our type
checker, and we're finding there's a lot
of uncertainty about how we should be
prioritizing features. Um there are
features like auto complete that have a
very large amount of engineering effort
necessary to produce a good feature, but
that don't really make sense for agentic
consumers. These kind of features are
feeling increasingly unimportant.
Uh there are other features that do feel
valuable to agents, like when they need
to modify a name or symbol across a
bunch of files. The LSP can do that much
more efficiently than it falling back to
tools like said.
Uh and there are human-facing features
which still feel important today. Uh for
example, for code review, using go to
definition or find all usages is still a
really nice thing, but these kind of
features aren't available in UIs like
GitHub, uh or their implementation is
not robust and does not rely on LSPs
under the hood.
So, part of what we're noticing here is
that the language server protocol isn't
designed for agents. There's a bunch of
stuff in there that's not relevant, and
we may want to consider designing new
protocols that are specifically for
agents to understand the semantics of
code.
Another roadmap item, uh plugins. Uh
historically, plugins have been low on
our list of priorities despite being a
very popular user request. They're hard
to get right, and they require exposing
internal concepts of our tools, which
we're worried will slow us down.
But now we might need to reassess that
prioritization.
The best way to get compounding benefits
from agents is to have them build their
own automations and feedback loops.
Allowing the agent to extend their tools
is a very powerful paradigm. For
example, the agent could define custom
lint rules to prevent itself from making
future mistakes. This could be a form of
memory for agents.
I want to talk about confidence next. Um
and here I'm talking about our own bar
for confidence in what we're what we're
telling users.
Um so, our current bar for confidence in
lint violations or warnings is very
high. Uh we would rather have false
negatives than false positives, because
we don't want to overwhelm humans with
diagnoses that may not be correct.
However, agents don't have this problem.
They won't get fatigued if they get too
many diagnostics. We might want more low
confidence lints that an agent can then
assess whether or not they're
applicable.
Um similarly, like Ruff has automatic
fixes for lint rules, and uh those fixes
generally guarantee that they won't
change the semantics of your code.
However,
uh if you can have an agent assess
whether or not a fix encounters one of
the edge cases that we're worried about,
but that are too challenging to
statically encode in the tool itself, we
might actually want to add a bunch more
unsafe fixes to Ruff that the agent can
apply and then assess after the fact.
Um a good example of that is like a huge
swaths of fixes in Ruff are marked as
unsafe right now because they might drop
comments, which you can put in a stupid
number of places in
uh Python syntax, and there's a lot of
ambiguity there. And like people are
prevented from using those features um
because we're worried about a comment
missing, but that's the kind of thing an
agent would catch very easily.
Uh one more roadmap item I want to talk
about is that our tools should have a
different model of trust with agentic
users.
Uh and this raises some questions about
features we have, like the ability to
ignore type errors.
Should the escape hatches that we give
humans uh exist in agentic harnesses?
Like should they be able to add no QAs?
Should they be able to add suppressions,
turn formatting off? Or do these just
enable the agent to behave poorly?
I think we should probably default to
constraining them more.
Uh another example is adding sandboxing
to UV. I actually have a pull request up
for this. Well, I pushed a commit, but
it's AI slop, so I haven't opened the
pull request yet.
Um
>> [laughter]
[gasps]
>> And this
uh this sandboxing makes like the tools
that you run with UVX have reduced
permissions. Uh they can't access the
file system outside the working
directory, and they can't access
secrets.
Um this kind of lockdown functionality
is useful to humans, but it's essential
when you're working with agents.
Sort of as a last roadmap item, I want
to talk about expanding the scope of
what we're working on.
Uh we're kind of considering everything
here. Um for example, should we build a
Python test runner that's focused on
agentic users?
Uh should we ensure that Python remains
competitive with other languages that
are becoming popular for agents, like
Go?
We could leverage TY to compile Python
code and improve execution times.
Should we invest in tooling outside of
Python, like with Rust? We work with the
Rust Rust a lot, and we work with Rust
with agents, and it suffers from really
slow feedback cycles because compile
times are so slow.
Or should we step back and continue to
focus on the human developer experience,
uh something that we're really
passionate about. Um we could build
higher-level tooling that orchestrates
agents. Is that within the scope of our
company?
It's hard to say. Uh
we're thinking about lots of things
here.
As a closing thought, I expect a lot of
disruption in the space of developer
tools. And something that keeps me up at
night is the idea that not far down the
line, the agents will just implement
purpose-built tools that address their
use cases.
There's already research showing that
agents that are allowed to construct
their own tools for their harness
outperform
um
harnesses that have been pre-built uh by
labs.
I'm not sure if this will happen soon. I
think that innovations in foundational
developer tooling require deep insights
and domain expertise that agents are not
currently capable of.
Um but it is this possibility that like
maybe maybe in a few years they'll just
be modifying UV to do these things that
they need, and they'll have a better job
assessing within their training cycles
uh and their fine-tuning
what is actually optimal for them.
Thank you very much.
>> [applause]
>> Awesome. Thank you very much. We have a
few minutes before lunch. Any questions?
Uh thank you. Um so, thinking about that
last thought about agents writing their
own tools got me thinking a little bit
about composability.
Um and so I'm wondering if you've given
any thought to the idea of perhaps
decomposing some of what UV and the rest
of the suite give you into smaller
pieces that agents could recombine in
new ways, so that they don't have to
write their own tools as much as take
those more discrete components and
recombine them as necessary. Yeah, I
think that really ties into the idea of
like plugins and extensions. Um
I think it's not necessarily realistic
for us to split UV into multiple smaller
components. Um
I think you would just be end up like
duplicating a lot of space uh with the
the repeated implementations that we
share. Um but I think more touch points
for integrating with UV.
Um we're adding more commands that
expose like UV's internals as machine
readable output, so that people can
build things that integrate with that.
Um we're exploring like adding hooks to
to common touch points in the system, so
you can build those kinds of extensions.
Yeah.
That's in the same line of the
Is a question of like how do you start
having like the agent itself? Because
you've talked about the the increase in
context that like the output of UV may
might create, but in a sense like the
agent is good at managing like maybe
those outputs and creating an output
that's proper for the actual agent doing
the work. Like Is is there like work on
agent in the loop of the tool itself? So
like not the one developing, but the one
like a separate one like a role specific
or context specific that just deals with
that. Like Yeah.
Um
I haven't really considered that. Um
that I mean of course like
there is an increasing trend of using uh
like sub agents to perform tasks to
reduce context overhead by having them,
you know, do the task and then report an
output. Um and I think that like if you
took like
this JSON output and you you used it a
plugin or extension to UV to inject an
agent in between that extracted what you
needed, um that's certainly a viable
option. I think it's going to be a lot
more expensive to run an agent to
perform that kind of task. Um
when you could instead just like, you
know, pick pick out the subset of a
machine readable output. Um that's like
sort of where the value of
uh deterministic and specialized tools
comes in is that we can
uh we can give you all the context that
you need and we can explain like we can
expose schemas and you can tell the
agent this is the schema and it can
choose what it needs without needing to
have another agent like stochastically
choose some subset that it might that it
might be relevant.
But yeah, it's an interesting idea.
Awesome. Thank you so much. Another
round of applause and then